uh okay so Merry Christmas it is Merry
Christmas time and what better day to
learn Shell redirection Shell
directional streams we're going to spend
hopefully less than an hour talking
about this and today we're also going to
compare several different shells um
because this thing that we're going to
talk about doing is has extensions that
are possible in certain shells and not
in others I know this was mostly been
about bash uh spoiler alert I am
banishing Bash from my life for 2025 I
am going to make an a summary of that
I'm also taking bash out of my book and
um as a scripting language but not as an
interactive shell I'll more on that
later so stay tuned today let's talk
about redirection okay and this is
pretty basic at this point in the video
you you've already watched all my other
videos and you you you you know about
standard input you know about Standard
air and you know about standard input
um okay so let's talk about those again
um when we do Echo when we do Echo hello
it goes to standard output right if we
wanted to uh read in uh a program you
know how to do that right we already did
that with read and line and we did a
little project last time but um and what
we're going to do now is so like we
already talked about redirecting that
stream to you know I did this right and
I didn't tell anybody what I was doing
so let's go through and let's actually
talk about this uh let's see uh ran back
crying but you do what you want you
broke up with bash
before I did I broke up with bash big
time before and then I ran back I did I
don't know if we're going to do bash
interactively but here's the thing it we
don't have to say only use bash
interactively and I I want you people
watching right now to be able to help me
make this decision because but before we
can have this convers you have to know
how all the redirections work so let's
let's get through that and let's have
the conversation people want to have the
conversation we were already talking
about that earlier so how do I take that
standard output and put it someplace
else what if I want to put it to a file
okay if I want to write that to a file
then I use this greater than sign it's
not greater than you'll hear us referred
to in technology as the right angle
bracket um people call it that's what
they mean and because it's you know it's
you know in that case it's not less than
right and that says I want to take
hellow and I want to Arrow it I want to
write it into a file so we'll put it
into Tempo and what that does by default
you may have no clobber on which will
say you can't do that if file exists uh
most people don't have that on by
default but what that does is it writes
out to that file it overwrites the file
zeros it out and writes the truncate
that's what they call it and then it
writes that new thing to the file okay
and now I can actually look at the file
with cat it'll show me what's in there
if I want to add um another thing to the
file I can put two of them and then that
just adds to the bottom of the file and
we C the file I mean this is this is
like shell 101 step right so now you
know so we can look at that thing um and
you you already know that cat will show
you all these add these to your notes
now you already know that um that cat
will show you these things a lot of
people don't know this but there's also
Tac which will actually reverse the
order of the lines and print them out
and there's two other commands to
memorize here head and we'll do head one
temp Fu that says show me the first line
and then we'll do tail dasu let's tell
you the bottom line and you can use tail
in addition with a-f so that if you add
something to the file uh it'll actually
show you as soon as it's added this is
useful for monitoring logs uh till F and
so then up here if I do if I do where's
my where's my cat so Echo there again
and it TR the end and you see you know
it adds it on to the end so that that is
everything to do with um redirecting
standard output uh to a file now what
you probably want to know after that we
already know how to edit files we talked
about that but um now we're going to do
uh let me see here so let's
actually um let's let's see now so we've
done that redirection out uh
occasionally something will have an
error and you need to like redirect the
error and you don't want to see this
this is a very common usage for
redirector the errors um in fact almost
always you're going to want to redirect
the errors let me give you a good
example if I do a find here and I say I
want it to
be uh I don't know maybe I want to have
it GP something right and I want to have
it exact you know about you don't know
about this command yet but if I did exac
uh GP I wanted to search for a thing H
for um hello and all the files um let's
see let's see if oh wait I have to
comment that out okay so you see all
that right there you see all those
errors there's a lot of Errors there and
you know that's not showing you your
useful information so this is one of
those cases where you'd want to shut it
up so this is one of those cases where
you would redirect it and so what you do
is you say I want to
redirect uh the errors which are coming
from two to Dev null and that says write
all instead of writing those to Output
to the terminal write them to devnull
which is just called the bit bucket so
it throws them away so now we only get
the things that we want to see and we
don't have to we're not forced to see
all the other stuff um you know there's
there's a bunch of files that are
written there and you know you see only
the files that exist that have the the
thing in there so that has been the
redirection of standard error now
occasionally you'll want to write to
standard error which we did in the to
being standard error yes and one is
standard out and zero is standard input
a lot of people don't know this but you
can actually Define your own file types
for output which you can combine in
interesting ways but that's out of the
scope of this beginner kind of stuff so
um but like what we should do now so
like let's say I want to write I want to
Echo something Echo uh there was a
problem but I don't want this to be in
the output maybe I want my program to
Output a number something and have an
error um and and so then uh we're going
to go ahead and do there was a problem
here and we're going to you know
normally that would just do that but now
we can make it go to the other stream
and the other stream is uh so by default
the main stream is one but we're going
to send it to standard a instead so you
put it you put that whatever the
Ampersand in front of there um it's not
an ENT is it yeah no it is okay you put
an ENT in front and it still goes to the
screen um but now it wouldn't be saved
if you were to put it to a file right so
I could say this now if I say write that
to Temp Fu you're going to see that fu
is empty now so cat temp Fu you see that
it's empty WC tempu has no lines in it
as well has one line over there oh wait
that's a fail I
failed I failed oh no I did it in the
wrong order oh I've done this before I
do this all the time actually yeah
that's a good error to do on
stream yeah
yeah that is a really good error to do
on stream the the order matters people
apparently as you just saw I always do
that wrong so be careful so here we go
so we have so this says redirect
standard um yeah it says redirect
standard output to Temp
bu but redirect standard errors
no wait is that what am I doing
there it's like right at cat
tempoo that's interesting okay yeah so I
guess it has to come first anyway you
can look up the order yourself the point
is I'm redirecting I'm re you're
redirecting standard error to
tempu no I'm not though that's the thing
this one I wasn't this this one is
redirected
that one is still working I I I have to
look this up yeah so anyway
two two is standard error
right
yeah actually what we're doing here is
not something you would normally do
because you would have two Echoes right
you'd have a log error and then you'd
have another program let's let's
actually do that so let's do that let's
say there was a problem we'll make that
write that to the errors okay this this
is a much better thing should we put it
in a script let's put it in a script but
um this is the same thing as a script so
Echo uh hello there okay so this is what
we want to actually have
appear and um it puts them it prints
them both out right but if I redirect
them to tempu you still see there was a
problem but temp fu is still there
because temp Fu was redirected and
standard error was redirected to there
right okay so if I wanted to if for this
particular thing if I wanted to shut up
the errors I could do this Dev null and
I it would still work so now there would
be no errors and tempu would be changed
when I put the parentheses around it
like that I turned it into a subshell
which essentially turns it into a script
and so that whole thing is as if it was
written in a little tiny script okay so
that's standard error standard out and
it's it's redirection and appending to a
file um there are are lots of other
things you can do here but 90% of the
stuff you're going to be doing is either
appending to a file redirecting to
devnull uh or um you know making a new
file uh by just you know writing your
output to a file that's the main way to
do that um so about this time it's worth
talking about uh piping so we haven't
talked this is all output stuff right
we're not going to talk about input we
already did with the read but we're
going to we're going to do output so
output more and more output okay so we
can say what if I wanted to take the
output of
Ls uh ls-1 let's say and I wanted to do
something with it right and there's lots
of things you can do here but I'm
actually going to use show you some fun
stuff we want to say I now grepp already
does this but we're just going to I'll
just play around with okay so let's take
that output and say I only want to see
the a do right so we can use the grip
command and we can say a do and that
would show you that there's only the a
do there right now more likely you want
to do something that only shows you know
you want to use a PR regular expression
and for this I'm going to use one of my
fun ones uh we're going to use uh
pae and I'm going to
say uh something like um let's say we
any anything that's got a an o in it
let's say anything that's got a dock in
it all right uh and
prints and say and say we write it
through that and so that prints out the
lines and we still have to organize the
lines and everything like that um but
you know you could do that similarly
with grep uh you could do GP anything
that's got dock in it same thing except
it takes out the blank lines um PA is
Pearl D AE which we're going to talk
about a L we're going to do a lot of
pearl in 2025 so I wanted to kind of
show you that in advance but um so
another thing too you can do with this
kind of filtering is you can transform
things so Pearl Dash uh this one we're
going to do uh PE and we're going to in
place we're going to make it all
lowercase so let's just say
LC and see what happens if we can do
that let's do that let's
say um let's do
LC let's see here
um I think we can just do this
one I think I have to reassign it
though yeah there probably an easier way
but that one will probably work there we
go so that's one way I could like
lowercase everything um and if I wanted
to make everything all uppercase I could
do UC see the point is is that we're
taking this text from one program and
we're sending it to another program in
this case Pearl which is 100 times
smaller than bash we just found that out
today um and more powerful it's at least
a thousand times more powerful than bash
so we're going to be doing a lot of
pearl in the new year um and and it's
because of these Transformations that
it's that it was created and it's pretty
amazing um and that's you know a pretty
realistic thing to do another thing too
you could do here is we could actually
on a separate line we could add how many
matches we have so if we actually um
well and if we wanted to add a match we
count them and there just a bunch of
little cool things you can do here um
and I don't want to get too sucked in
the Weeds on this this is just really
fun but what I'm trying to mainly tell
you is that this pipe here says take the
standard output and attach it to the
standard input there are other simpler
things to do so you can send it to WC it
counts how many numbers of lines here if
you only wanted to count the line
numbers um you could do- L and so this
this idea of attaching things in a pipe
is the that is the essence of the Unix
philosophy and that is also the base
essence of Unix filters um you can do
all kinds of things this way so you can
say this you can say
Echo uh you know 23
* uh times blah blah blah and you can
send that to a command line calculator
and it will calculate the number for you
that exact thing can be done within a
file while you're editing it so in fact
let's take the exact code and use it as
a filter and we're going to do temp Fu
and we're going to write the same code
right here as if we had just like what
we were like writing a blog or something
and we want to do some math right and we
just want to put that math here so um so
there it is we don't need the echo
anymore um in fact we don't need any of
that we can just get rid of all that and
now we can just do bang bang and send it
to the BC command and that line will be
replaced with its output why because of
the way way Unix Works Vim filters are
based on Unix Unix is you know largely a
bunch of things that pipe their text
input to something else and that's how
they work and so everything's designed
to take standard input and do standard
output whether it be something as simple
as sorting everything here boom boom
sort right now I could I could have done
that same command let's see how I would
do that by by just taking the output of
that command if I were to take that
command let's say another one so what
I'm trying so let's do this one okay so
let's take that command and and let's
use the cat command don't do that
actually no let's do the let's do the
input now should we do cat well let's
show you okay so what does cat do cat
dumps stuff out right we're gonna don't
do what we're about to do but I'm going
to show you this is usually an anti-
pattern because it it masks things but
you could cat you can pipe it into what
right so let's do this into
sort right so you can do and it gives a
thing but now you can take it into sort
now that they're together you can set it
to another command call Unique and then
it cuts out all the ones that are unique
right and then maybe maybe you only want
the ones that have a in them so we grip
ad you see how this works right so you
can incrementally build up these
pipelines uh that do this kind of thing
and that would be one of the cases where
you might want to C the pile normally
though um you would you would want to do
this and this this introduces
redirection of standard input so instead
of you know angled right we're going to
go angle left now and we're going to say
this we're going to say I want to sort
everything in this file now this you
know sort I think takes a file name yeah
sort a lot of these programs will
actually take a file name and they'll
assume that but some don't some you have
to pass a thing and in fact I don't
think WC does let's see WC WC does okay
so WC does do the file but um you can
do- L but most programs are also
designed to take standard input so that
says take that in right now you can
actually cat is one of those things
right so cat takes either an argument
which is the file name you can take
several file names actually and it'll
it'll concatenate all of them together
or you can send something to cat and
it'll just send it out right it'll send
the output so you can do cat and you can
send it like that and it you know it
outputs the thing um there there are a
number of Tricks here one of the tricks
is that you can put that entire file
into a variable using the redirect so
you can do this you can say uh you can
say bar let's
see uh F
content F content equals and you
redirect temp Fu and now now it's saved
now it's saved into a variable and you
can Echo who content and it'll have all
the stuff in there but you notice how it
put it all together on a different line
you know why cuz Echo if you print up
that watch it'll be it'll only do the
first one that's because there's not
quot quotes there yeah Shel would be
yelling at us for not doing quotes there
yeah there we go so as you can see and
you got a little you get a little lesson
in Shell expansion there right because I
didn't G around it and it only looked at
the first thing because it just replaced
it onto the line at that point which is
what it does by default which can be
dangerous um she said H yeah so so that
has been you know there's are some
tricks uh for standard input so you can
actually do the same thing uh
so we could do this we can say while
read- R line you guys know about reading
is reading a line we already did that
when we did our prompt program right and
you can do ECHO line done and then we
can send in tempu and that will give it
every line and this is kind of cool
because you know it's uh if you wanted
to redirect um a command you could do
that if to redirect a command you just
put the command here ls-1 and that'll
redirect that thing and you could if you
wanted to do this and you can say Echo
uh prefix you know colon line you could
ENT to a prefix in front of the line
like that you know so that is an example
of you know reading standard input into
with think you could it could be you
could do it through a for Loop you could
do it through a while loop um and we
learned those already we learned for and
while already um so there's a there's a
bunch of really cool little tricks that
you can do that um and
so so that that is you know it that's
that's pretty much file redirection
indirection okay that everything we
talked about so far about standard input
standard output and and and error
applies to every Unix like shell that's
ever been made every postic compliant
shell uh all the way back since 1979 and
because it's fundamentally a part of how
the Unix command line has always worked
um now there are some addition s um to
to this that have made it easier to do
things um that are not supported by all
po compliance shells and a couple of
them at least one of them is really
important it's really valuable and that
is what's called a he string so um and
what it does there's two there's two
things there's a hear Dock and there's a
hear string so what what a hear string
does um uh where is there two because
this here means means take this into a
file okay so let's this means anytime
there was a file so let's let me let me
that's what I'm doing here so instead of
it being temp
file okay so when you when you do the
here from a file so anytime you have
this it says send the the you know that
file send that file as input to the
thing that's what it's saying send the
file as standard input into the thing
it's redirecting from the file into this
thing right here this program and the
trick that I did here this is one of
those tricks where this says well we
don't have a file we want to pretend
like ls-1 the output of that was written
to a file and then read into and we
could do that indirectly if we wanted to
right we could do ls-1 temp uh LS output
and in the old days we had to do this
and and then we would do something like
this we would say uh you know we'd have
temp
uh uh and we would actually make
temporary directories for this and stuff
but you can get away with just skipping
that step
oops output um all right so you see the
point it's exactly the same as as
replacing that step with that so this
just says take take that take that
command and use the command as if it
were in a
file and it produces a file description
and everything in case you're wondering
so um yeah so that says it actually the
the parentheses mean a subshell that it
says run this stuff in a subshell and
whatever comes out of there pretend like
it's in a file temporarily and then use
that as a file and send it in okay so
now there's there's another angle on
this and that this is it right here so
if I could say this um and this is this
is where we want to say I want to send
in a few strings right so I can say some
uh thing I don't know if you even can do
line returns here I don't think you can
nope you can't you
can't so this is called a hear
string uh just about everything Network
graphics cards R binaries yes you
can I said parentheses equals a subshell
didn't I it does parentheses means the
subshell no matter what yeah usually
always it means a subshell
um something so the only time I've ever
used this is when I wanted to cheat okay
there's some for some reason some
program is designed to take standard
input and only standard input and there
are pro programs out there like that and
ENT comes to mine and um you want to
send just a single string as the first
line of out of of input that's what this
does this is called a hear string
and um what it says is this isn't a
string at all this is a file that's got
one line in it that is called something
and by the way you you we just tried
making it into two lines and I don't
think you can I think there has to be a
here dock for that um uh so it needs no
you're missing a a uh you need two of
them you need this one right here and
then a space and then you need the other
one next to the parentheses and they
have to be connected into the
parentheses otherwise it won't work okay
so so here we go we've got this one here
and we have something preferred
something so this is called a hear
string um I've never used this for
anything more than just a single
string um but that is sometimes useful
uh that is an exceptional thing though
that is not supported in
any shell besides bash um you know the
the the EXT shells like like bash and
and Zell supported um it is not
supported in dash Ash or kshell actually
I think it is supported in Kell didn't
we didn't we already test it I think
Kell supports it I think that's where it
came from Kell is a really old uh shell
extension let me let me just check and
see yeah okay so Kell supports it so
Kell came shell
history um is special actually let's try
that too cat
um ls- LS ls-
L okay so so that's supported by quell
as well um yeah that's the special token
that means hey this is a fish kind of
thing so Kell supports those things and
the very last one that we're going to
have which which you almost never use
interactively from a shell so let's
actually put this in a script um so
we'll put this in our uh what we was our
sample
test what was it called lab sample I
don't remember yeah so let's put this in
here let's say um let's copy prompt
to
uh let's say I don't know what to call
it
um I'm trying to think of something we
should do for this this is never
something I have to teach in any other
of the languages so trying to think of
something on the Fly what could we call
it we could call
it um
long we'll just call it
long and CD in the long
description and I've got you using user
b bash which I'm never going to do again
but that's another video um anyway we
got all this code and stuff let's do
this I want to say I have I have a lot
of stuff I want to put on lots of
different lines right so I could do uh
one line two lines three
lines right and and I could just do this
so you can do long and that is fine
right um but what if I wanted to do
something else with it what if I what if
I wanted to use that as input
someplace um I mean you know I could do
that right I could do
wild while read D-
rline do
Echo uh line line done and then I could
send that um with a string
variable yeah but see how it's not happy
now yeah it's going to it's going to
yell at
me all right so this actually might
work yeah so that's you see that's a
here um this space is not the token no
you need to get rid of the
space yeah there's two different less
than signs there's one before it and
then there's one out I always forget
that so anyway um you see how the stuff
at the top and the bottom is kind of
like do we really want that that does
work right but there's another thing you
can do here and it's a little bit
cleaner than this and you see how this
gives you that extra line above it and
stuff you can't put this on a different
line like that it doesn't work so
there's another thing it's called a he
Dock and this is supported in every
version of of Unix that there is and you
get rid of one of these things and then
you put the name
of the thing to look for at the end eom
in this case all right and it says oops
we get rid of this here okay and now
that's called a here do and what that
says is okay get ready whatever comes on
the next line is the beginning of what
I'm going to send you and I'm going to
keep reading until I get to the end of
this message it could be anything e is
generally preferred for that so now I
can run it like this I can run long and
it does the whole thing and I don't get
those extra lines because of the string
right and this is pretty frequent this
is there's a lot of common uses cases
for this um let's say you wanted to put
an extensively long comment in your code
you can use it with the UN this is
called the uh the nlop it's just a colon
by itself it doesn't do anything but you
can send eom and can say this is a very
long
descriptive uh uh uh comment I guarantee
you at least one Unix veteran just saw
that and didn't know you could do this
it's a very common thing to do um and
you know it's it's it's kind of worth
doing except for I did it
wrong I totally did it wrong it might be
helpful for me to do it right yeah you
can yeah don't use end of a file it's a
different thing uh eof is a totally
different thing I would just end a
message if you was you so uh so there
you go so we got that you notice that
this did not print anywhere and it's
just easy to write a long comment that
way um if I wanted to print the comment
you know what to do right I would just
have to do print here Echo and that
would um would do it
um uh actually I'm sorry cat right I
forgot to say that because this is an
incoming this is the same as like
sending in standard input I always I
always screw that up so you could go
like this and it suddenly it'll say it
uh you know you can replace with the cat
but if you just put the null op there
there then it just it it just won't do
it okay so um so you don't put star in
front of you there um you can use eof if
you want but eof means end of file and
that's not what this is right so this is
really this is just a token okay there's
one last thing to consider here and that
is the standard shellway so you're like
wouldn't it be great it feels like it's
kind of invading my space here right I
wish it were not doing that uh and by
the way since this is in a scripts why
are we cramming this all into multiple
lines why don't we just put it here and
save it there we go okay so yeah there
we go AR Rob but what it' be nice if
this were kind of indented and it
weren't kind of all mushed together well
if we put a dash here then we get
indentation and I don't know if you
noticed this but um but this is what you
get yeah Tel instead it's even
slower why you still I'm still running
our build on TCL yeah so you can I mean
you can use you can script it bash if
you want I'm I'm just going to try to
deposit shell and pearl for everything
so you saw what I did here as soon as I
put a dash in there shell check and
shell upmt very happily set list they
set my my lines to have tabs in the
front of them and it's very important
that you understand this indentation in
Shell standard shell standard shell
indentation is tabs not spaces and I
know if you've noticed but every time I
run sh fmt when I save it puts a tab
there and I don't care about tabs versus
spaces because I'm using sh fmt if
you're not doing that you're doing more
work than you have to and there are a
lot of people who are veterans who are
doing more work than they have to I
promise you and so don't do that don't
be them just just standardize on sh fmt
and I mean I even got indentation for
free just by adding the dash when I
saved because shell fmt knows about it
it's like okay you want to indent you're
thinking oh is it going to print with
indentation nope it's not because why
because it knows to trim that
indentation um if you want you can also
have this be a tab uh if if you really
want it can be a tab as well uh I'm
pretty sure so you can have it be really
clean and you know have the whole thing
be indented that is also valid um
although my sh fmt is fond of putting it
back over there for me so I kind of have
to convince it to not do that but it's
it's not happy right now so I'm just
going to keep it that way the point of
it is this is called a here dock here
strings are three here docs are two um
there are occasions when you might want
to put a variable in here so let's say
uh uh name equals Rob or something two
lines uh and I want to Robin here or
name and you can tell from my my
formatter that this is considered a
variable at this point okay and this
will actually print the variable inside
of there and that's because the default
context for a here Doc is double quotes
these are exactly equivalent it'll
probably change it uh okay oh wait maybe
not that's
interesting
huh ah I thought I thought that was
going to allow quotations I guess
not I guess I was wrong on
that I all this time I thought those two
were the same all right well they're not
so the other one is single quotes right
if you put single quotes it says it's
not used anymore because I just stopped
it from being used uh when you put
single quotes or double quotes there
apparently um that says that your your
everything in the eom block is going to
ignore variables completely um and this
is actually one of the reasons you would
do this is like if you wanted to include
back ticks something you know it would
actually if you don't do that it'll try
to run that right and and that is
something you could do you could have it
be like ls- L you know and have that be
a back tick Andor a thing and it will
actually run it but that's probably not
what you want right so um say it says
yeah that's old all right so if but if
you do this you can say long and you say
it actually injects into the middle of
your thing the ls command because it's
not doing if you wanted to actually
print it out you put the quotes around
it and that'll do the right thing so
that's it that's it we've learned about
standard out we learned about standard
input um we've learned about
redirections and we learned about
pipelines probably the only thing left
to tell you about pipelines is what if
you want to see the output but also
rewrite it to a file so there is one
command for this that's really important
that you know it's called T and what T
does is it splits the standard output
stream and yeah it splits the standard
output stream sends it to you and also
writes it to a file this is particularly
useful if you're like monitoring logs or
something and you want to copy all those
logs to go back to but you still want to
see them now you can accomplish the same
thing by redirecting your output to a
log file and then tail Das fing the log
file which we already did we just did
that but T kind of does the same thing
so you could say you know while true do
Echo hello um and you know uh sleep uh3
uh and then done right it's just going
to print hell but let's like if we print
that to a file temp temp hellos right I
can't see it I can't see it or can I
right I could I could do this tell DF
temp hos and I can see it coming now you
can't actually let's add the date stamp
to it so you guys can see it it it's
date uh I'll see Hello on uh date and so
okay so now we can do tail-f and we see
each state and it's how this getting
written uh all right so actually we
should to make it more fun let's make it
random color shall we so
Rand
Rand uh
color
hello how about that I wonder if that'll
tell properly yeah there we go so
there's our hellos coming in and we did
the random color thing already in
another
video and you can see them coming in now
if but if you wanted I I personally
don't use T that much because I I always
forget to do it and it's just just it's
just as easy to go tell the file you
know so but if you wanted to start the
program and have it be readable while
you were doing it instead of redirecting
to hello like this you just do you pipe
it to T instead and you see how it takes
an argument as the file name and stead
of of that and now if you go down here
and we do our tail again you'll see it's
the same exact output okay so now now we
get we get the te output and we get the
output from uh just a regular ta that
but you can see that they're the same
thing they're ultimately the same thing
uh you know and the downside of of of of
having T there is that if you wanted to
you know change the way you viewed it or
something you know it would be now if
you you can you can also o send this
into a pager too if you want you can
send it to a pager like less or more and
it will you know happily page for you
watch it'll stop okay because it's still
sending them but now I'm hitting space
to see the next ones and catching up
right so again the same thing if you
want to if you want to be able to stop
while you're doing and I don't know if
you can can grasp this right now but
this this is a particular command that
is a really good one to end our
conversation about bash programming and
scripting because I just did a lot of
things in this line at the same time
that illustrate every single thing that
we talked about okay we we just if you
look at this line right here over the
last you know with three or four
sessions of of bash scripting that we've
been doing for the holiday boosts this
line that we just did kind of
encapsulates a little bit of every
single thing we've done we have a
Boolean type we have strings we have
embedded right here we have an embedded
subshell command here we have the same
exact subshell command using back ticks
instead of this notation we're echoing
we we've got line returns for that for
those individual lines we are piping to
T so we got standard output coming in
with t-f down here uh we're actually
using you know we're we're we're using
standard input we're tailing the program
against standard input um you know we've
got a pager here which we talked about
how to page through the different things
you want to see we got the color going
on so there's a lot going on on this
single command line and we kind of just
wrote that together really quickly
that's the power of Unix and I'm saying
Unix because Unix is the origination of
this Linux is the fanfiction of Unix on
at the end of the day it really is and
Unix is the true Master Unix is the true
OG system that Linux has has built
itself around and quite frankly it's an
interesting point we're going talk about
this later but I still think Unix is
going to dominate Unix is you know and I
I personally like BSD Unix more than
Linux they're all Unix like operating
system so listen agree to disagree if
you like something else about another
one but they all originated with this
this absolutely brilliant idea from Ken
Thompson and the Gang to pipe together
in Unix philosophy little things that do
one thing really well and that integrate
with others that play nice with others
you know a lot of people forget that
second couplet of that you know Unix
philosophy statement the do one thing
well that's regularly cited as the Unix
philosophy but it's not that's only half
of it do one thing well and integrate
well I say play nice with others and
that's that is what and then use text
that you can do the search for Unix
philosophy you'll see all of that
there's way more than I would ever uh
want to cover in a video but that that
is the essence of Unix philosophy that's
where the power comes from and I hope
you've seen how mastering the Unix
philosophy the idea of piping and
filtering and one thing you know re
connecting one thing and Bim filters and
all that stuff which most Vim people
have no idea about Vim filters at all
like oh what plug-in are you using I'm
not using a plugin I'm using Unix and
I've been doing it since
1996 so you know this isn't something
that it needs to plug in so if you truly
I I honestly believe this friends if you
learn Unix the right way your your the
way that impacts what you learn
everything else will be impacted by that
decision and and we're going to talk
about some of those other things later
um that will extend your your terminal
based speed and integration and we're
going to talk about you know why you
should never use set or o and you should
use Pearl instead there's that's a very
hot topic a hot opinion people think I'm
crazy but I'm going to make the case
completely for that um and you know what
go how does go even play into this right
when would you want to write something
in go instead of bash or Pearl or or or
you know kshell or zshell which of the
shells is the best and everything and
quite frankly your interactive shell it
really doesn't matter because your
interactive shell as long as it's Unix
like you're fine so so next time
somebody wants to fight with you about
Zell versus bash versus fish just say it
doesn't matter as long as you understand
the essentials of shell scripting that
you just learned you can use those
anywhere and it'll just work right it'll
just work there's a few few things that
don't work and I actually mentioned some
parameter expansion ideas uh and things
that you could use um that work in Kell
Zell and Bash but I prefer to not
mention them at this point because um
they're quite frankly they're better
done in Pearl and that includes like
converting something to lower case and
you'll have to stay tuned and watch
another video about that uh later which
which I will do um uh so there are a lot
of programming languages out there to
learn uh uh but if you right now the
your your main take is I I just want to
be able to use my shell interactively
the goal of this the these last three
videos or five videos or so has been
being able to to mostly to use your
command line appropriately I started
kind of incorrectly by trying to model
this part after after bash or after
Python and and quickly realize that
that's really not the that's really not
the point here the point here is for you
to be good on the interactive command
line in such a way that you can
understand your your bash RC or your
Zell RC file when you go to customize uh
your shell later which is going to be
the next video so the next video but I
told you to use bash and it was the only
way to go I totally changed my mind yep
I did I changed my mind I've been
talking about it all morning you're GNA
have to watch the big long live video
version if you want to watch that
instead um you can watch that but uh I
was wrong uh I told people for two years
that they should just use bash as the
only show that they should ever write in
uh for lots of reasons I'm writing an
I'm going to do a whole video about how
wrong I was on that and uh I'm going to
cite the reasons that I was wrong on
that and I'm going to tell you why I
think that now and if you if stay tuned
for that video uh I there's nothing
wrong with learning bash particularly as
an interactive shell welcome to
flip-flop Rob that is I am flipflop Rob
I I I test something for an extensive
amount of time and then when something
goes bad I change my mind back and if
you don't like that you're in the wrong
place you're also in the wrong
career because if you think things are
going to stay static in technology this
is a wrong place for you to be my
friends Merry Christmas and we'll see
you
later hey it's the guy that flip-flops
yep that's me yes I consider it a badge
of honor that I do do you have many
people don't flip-flop and stay with the
old thing and then they retire because
they don't want to learn a new language
or they don't want to take in something
new I never want to be that guy I never
want to be that guy I I'll see a bit